<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe and compendious exposition vpon the Psalme called Deprofundis which haue bene And presentelye is horrible and detestable. Abused in the churche of God. And now translated to the trew sens: to Gods glorie &amp;to the edification and confort of his church. By M. Roberte Richardson batchelere of diuinetie and minister in Londen.</title>
            <title>Briefe and compendious exposition upon the Psalme called Deprofundis which have bene.</title>
            <author>Richardson, Robert, minister in London.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1570</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10744</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21021</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105747</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841473</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841473</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6058</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10744)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6058)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 717:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe and compendious exposition vpon the Psalme called Deprofundis which haue bene And presentelye is horrible and detestable. Abused in the churche of God. And now translated to the trew sens: to Gods glorie &amp;to the edification and confort of his church. By M. Roberte Richardson batchelere of diuinetie and minister in Londen.</title>
                  <title>Briefe and compendious exposition upon the Psalme called Deprofundis which have bene.</title>
                  <author>Richardson, Robert, minister in London.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas Purfoote for William Norton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1570]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalmes CXXIX --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6058:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6058:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ A Briefe and Compendious ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition vpon the Pſalme called <hi>Deprofundis</hi> which haue bene. And preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telye is horrible and deteſtable. Abuſed in the Churche of God.</p>
            <p>And now tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the trew ſens: to Gods glorie &amp; to the Edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and confort of his Church. By M. Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berte Richardſon Batchelere of diuinetie And Miniſter in Londen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="commentary_on_Psalm_n129__Vulg">
            <pb facs="tcp:6058:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6058:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>¶</hi> A BREVE AND compe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dious expoſition vpon <hi>the Pſalme called Deprofundis.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Auide the greate</hi> Kinge of Ieruſalem, and Prince of Prophetes decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vnto vs the pſalmes to be of an excellent vertue by this his ſayinges. <hi>2. reg. 23 Spiritus domini loquutus eſt per me &amp; ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo eius per lingua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> And <hi>10.</hi> parala. <hi>28 Omnia veneru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t mihi ſcripta manu Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni.</hi> By this his ſayinges he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſeth the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye Ghoſt to be the Authore of the pſalmes, and him ſelfe to be the Inſtrumente by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the holy Goſt openeth them vnto vs and to all godlye by Dauides tou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, and how they come vnto him written by the hande of the Lord, to the end that we ſhold vſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the prologue of this Pſalme declareth brieflye ſhortelye and learnedlye for it proffire no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge to reade and knowe many thinges &amp; to miſknowe God and his worde by whom be is onlye knowen, &amp; the true meaking and ſenſe of the ſame for Chriſte ſayde him ſelfe. <hi>luc. 10. Porro vnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt neceſſariu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> That is to ſay verely one thinge is neceſſary whiche is
<pb facs="tcp:6058:3"/>the knowledge of his word, this he ſayd whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he gaue the Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t betwixt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> two ſiſters Marie &amp; Martha, for marie ſat at his feete &amp; hard the word, wherfore he ſayd. Mary hath choſen y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſte part which ſhal neuer be taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hyr.<note place="margin">Mat <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ergo beati qui audiunt verbu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Dei.</hi> Bleſſed are thoſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> heare the worde of god, &amp; beleueth it, &amp; keepeth it to the end, for thy be ſure of eternall lyfe world without end. And heare not without the knowledge of Gods word god was neuer knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nor is not kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, therfore ſayth ſ. Iero. <hi>Creature no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> habe us noticia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> creatoris picus eſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ieronim. Sapie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>15</hi>
               </note> That is to ſay The creature not hauinge knowledge of the creatore is but a beaſt, &amp; the wiſe man ſayth. <hi>Vanus eſt omnis homo in quo no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ineſt ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia Dei.</hi> that is to ſay. Euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is but vay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knowledge of god. wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I do thinke it neceſſary, fyrſte to declare what is God, &amp; where we ſholde worſhippe and Iuuocate himſelf. <hi>Humana ratio Deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non cognoſcit.</hi> wherefore I knowledge it were but preſumptuouſe to gather ſuch thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges vpon my head or to gather it vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other mens brayne, I coulde neuer reade yet hym that could comprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de by his learning witte or ſenſes the eſſence of God, nor yet vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtode y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſame, nor yet fully vnderſtod the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the ſonne &amp; the moone. Ergo much
<pb facs="tcp:6058:3"/>leſſe the Diuine ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God for. <hi>Imme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum definire non poteſt.</hi> That is to ſay god is vnmiſerable Incomprehenſible and can not be by vs defyned, but it ſuffiſethe vs to know god, to be ſuche one as he hath reuey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto vs by his word. Now I go to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare where he ſholde, be Inuocated &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped. <hi>Prophetae nouerunt illum eſſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um cuius verbum promiſionis &amp; cultu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bueru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</hi> That is to ſay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prothets knew him to be god, whoſe holy worde promiſſes and worſhippinge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they had by his worde, the Iewes, Turckes &amp; papiſtes ſeekes to know &amp; come to God by their cogitacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions &amp; Imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s without his holy wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de or ells tranſlating his worde fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne ſence &amp; true right vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding. <hi>Sed Prophetae nouerunt Deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſe. Impropicia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ei qui ſi allegaret verbo &amp; loquebatur qualis fuerit in verbo &amp; in culto ſuo nec ali ter loqui ac cogitare debemꝰ nos qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis eſt in noſtro ꝓpiciatorio chriſto.</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſaye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophets did knowe god to be in his propiciatory which I vnderſtand to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer that was ſet aboue the Arke to the which he bounde him ſelfe and ſpake oute of it how he was in his woorde, and worſhippin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge ſuche lyke wee ſhoulde not ſpeake nor thincke other wyſe, then hee is in oure
<pb facs="tcp:6058:4"/>propiciatory Chriſte, ſo teſtifieth Paule ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge. <hi>Deus erat in Chriſto mundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cillians ſibi.</hi> God was in chriſt reconcilyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world to him ſelf: ſo ſayth Chriſt him ſelf to Philip his Apoſtell. <hi>Qui me vidit, &amp; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem meu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vidit.</hi> who ſeeth me ſeeth my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>Et nemo venit ad patrem niſi per me.</hi> That is no man can come to my Father, but onelye by me. Heare wee maye note a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall rule in all the pſalmes and in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcripture to be kepte that in the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment all prayers was to God in Sion: now y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> temple deſtroyed God rayſed vp a nother temple whiche is Chriſte in this temple hee wold be onlye ſoughte, founde, &amp; worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped. <hi>Nec extra illum vllu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Deum inuenies.</hi> And beſydes him, thou ſhalte fynde no god but onlye Idolatrie therfore let vs beholde him and thou ſhalte ſe the Father. The holy Iewes that dwelte in Syon, which neglec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that place, all be it that they had the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ſacrifices and prayinge the ſame wordes neuertheleſſe they committed Idolatrie for becauſe they did agaynſte the precepte &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundemente of God, whiche he declared, that he wolde be worſhipped in Ieruſalem but now in the temple which is Chriſt, and beſydes that temple there is no God wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped but the Deuil, &amp; becauſe the Iewes
<pb facs="tcp:6058:4"/>Turckes and Papiſtes praiſe much &amp; many pſalmes with pleaſaunt titles, and do ſaye: Our Father which arte in heauen. &amp;c. But becauſe they contenue his holye and infalla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble worde and by violence do perſecute the ſame, as now do oure Papiſtes they obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne no frute nor commoditie at the handes of God therof, but mere Idolatrie,<note place="margin">Nota.</note> Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie and loſſe of tyme, &amp; note, where Chriſt is God is, there is the hole deuinitie founde in him, &amp; this is the God that ſayde. The ſeede of the woman ſhall bruſe thy head.<note place="margin">Geneſis.</note> Heare to this ſayinges Chriſt is promiſed and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> only ſacrifice for the ſinnes of the worlde and the triumphante victorye, Hell the Deuill and ſinne. Therfore let vs all ſay with Paule. <hi>Deo gratias qui dedit nobis victoriam per Chriſtum.</hi> Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes be to god that hath geuen vs the victorie by Chriſt for there is no God but hee that was borne of the Virgins boſome both God and man as is aforeſayde and further more he hym ſelfe ſayth beleue ye not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Father is in me &amp; I in my father he that ſeeth me ſeeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> father and he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> knoweth me knowethe my Father let this therfore be the finall concluſion that God will not be ſoughte found nor here our Prayers whithoute dure propiciatory Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte lette vs therefore call to remembraunce
<pb facs="tcp:6058:5"/>oure greate and deepe ignoraunce that haue ſought him at ſtocke and ſtone and in manye places beyonde home. &amp;c. God graunte vs his grace to acknowledge and repente this, and to be aſhamed of the ſame ignoraunce. Amen.</p>
            <div type="prologue">
               <head>
                  <hi>¶</hi> The Prologue.</head>
               <p>¶ we reade of Dauid that he gaue the ſame pſalmes to the prieſts &amp; leuites to be prayde ſonge and ſaid &amp; plaide vpon the Cimballes Pſalteres, Harpes, wyth many other plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt inſtrumentes prayſing god, worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping God, &amp; geuinge thankes to God, &amp; an example to vs to doe the ſame with gladnes and minde of hart, ſpirite, and ſoule &amp; ſtrong faith with our ſpirituall inſtruments and ſo Saincte Paule exhortethe vs. <hi>Epheſ. 5. Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentes vobis metipſis in Pſalmis &amp; Imnis cantantes &amp; melodiam facientes in cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus veſtris Domino Gratias agentes Ieſu Chriſto Redemptori noſtro. &amp;c.</hi> that is to ſaye ſpeakinge and prayinge to your ſelues in pſalmes, in ſinging and reioyſing in your hartes geninge thankes to Ieſu Chriſt oure Sauiour, &amp;c. So Salomon whyche builded the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple after the diſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the holy goſt geuynge to his Father Dauide ſo Salomon
<pb facs="tcp:6058:5"/>builded the temple as Dauid comaunded, in <hi>Monte Morea,</hi> with aſſenſe of fiftene degres after the example that was geuen, and in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerye degree was ſounge and playde by the Aſcendentes one of this pſalmes whyche is called the .xv. Pſalines knoweledging and confeſſyng the manyfolde benefices of God and their owne filthie ſinfulnes goinge vp theſe degrees into the temple ſynginge and praying with gladneſſe of harte and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledginge at the remiſſion of ſinnes is freelye graunted and geuen to vs of God by Ieſu Chriſte and ſo it profite the and is fruitefull vnto vs to acknowledge the ſame in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnynge of all oure prayers goynge to the remple or elles all oure doynges is loſte for ſo muche as they are not of ſtronge faythe wythoute all doubtinge and diſparynge of Goddes hopinge hearinge and free mercye graunting which God graunt all Chriſtians to haue. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="title">
               <head>De Profundis.</head>
               <p>¶ Thys is the Pſalme of the whyche I entende briefelye to wrytte vppon and is the mooſte comfortable and Heauenlye amongeſt all the pſalmes and this is the .C.xxxi. and in ſome bookes .xxix. amonge the
<pb facs="tcp:6058:6"/>number of pſalmes and the .xi. pſalme that was ſonge vppon the Grees by the prieſtes and lenites and the .vj. pſalme of the peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiall pſalmes called the .vij. pſalmes com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>menlye ioyned in confeſſion by ignoraunte prieſts and Fryers in ſatiſfaction for ſynne and this pſalme the Popiſhe dyd burie and kepe from the knowledge of the people the true ſence and meaning confeſſinge and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendinge that it was onelye a prayer for the deade and for the ſoules of Purgatorie and ſo buryinge it, committed ſacrilege and yet preſently do. Albeit the holye ghoſt the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thore of this pſalme did inſtitute and ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it to be a prayer of penitent ſinners be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of life which do knowledge their ſinnes and repenting the ſame from the bottome of their hartes. If anye learned man pleaſe to reade this lytle pſalme to the ende, he ſhall not finde one iott nor one worde in it for the dead but as is aforeſaid for the penitents on life, and ſo the poore people alas for pitye was for couetonſnes kept in Ignerance and blindnes and yet ſtill is in many countryes and places, ſo periſhed from the vſe of the quicke penitents an incomparable treaſure and a moſt godlye knowledge of our iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation I haue ſeene my ſelfe in Rome one Cardinall deade and brought into a churche
<pb facs="tcp:6058:6"/>and laide on a faire tombe couered with vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet bare faced his berde newe ſhauen, a faire miter on hys heade, wyth coſtlye precious ſtones and coſtlye newe gloues vppon hys hands full of ringes hoſe of ſylke and San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalles on his feete with ſtones, and one gret gentleman on euery ſide of him bare headed with veluet gownes and white roddes in their handes and a yarde of taffetie bounde faſte at the ende of the roddes kepyng away the flyes from his face, continuallye as the cuſtome is in Italie when ye dine at the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble amonge ſeruaunts or in your lodginges or houſes. And at that time I ſawe come in ſuch a number of Friers monckes &amp; Nones ſmyling at with my ſelfe remembring a com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon ſayinge in Scotlaude Fryers a newe a new and a new redd and white, white and blacke blonkat and blewe and they went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the dead Cardinales tombe but once a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, for lacke of time or elles euerye order could not haue their courſe, I ſay they went aboute the tombe with coſtlye odoriferous ſenſors ſenſing and ſynging the dead Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, ſome with the firſt verſe of <hi>Deprofun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis,</hi> for briefenes ſome with <hi>Libera me Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi> ſome with <hi>Qui lazarum Reſuſcitaſti,</hi> ſome wyth <hi>Requiem aeternam,</hi> ſome wyth <hi>Peccante me quotidie &amp; non penitente
<pb facs="tcp:6058:7"/>Timor mortis co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>turbat me.</hi> And with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie ſuche like many reſponſories contayned in the dirigie very briefe. The nomber of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious,<note place="margin">Rome.</note> ſuperſtitious men and women was ſo greate that they coulde not haue time but once to go about the tombe, herein you may marke howe greate Cities and notable men haue ben drowned &amp; myred with this great ignoraunce. in ſo much as thoughe that thys godlye Pſalme ſerued nothinge but for the deade in purgatorye &amp; nothing at all for the penitentes of life as ye ſhal heare hereafter. if there be anye ſuthe purgatories or no and how manye countres &amp; cites are deceiued by this falſe doctrine I ſpeake onlye of thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue knowen &amp; ſeene as at Rome, Paris, Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Bononia Dei Gratia, flore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia, Bella Pauia,</hi> where manye learned men be &amp; nowe thankes be to god daylye encreaſed but alas many blind doctors, as doctors dandiprates doctors dueſaſe &amp; doctors ſophiſters promo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted by the Pope Cardinalls, Biſhopes, and Abbottes &amp; other greate men of their leuine by whom periſhe the true vſe of this godlye and diuine pſalme and prayer.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Paris.</head>
               <p>¶ I haue knowen and ſene in Paris .vij.
<pb facs="tcp:6058:7"/>thouſandes poore ſtudentes and poore men y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> could reade or ſay the <hi>Deprofundis</hi> hyred before all ſoules daye to ſit all that nighte with Lanternes and Candells vppon their huſbandes, wifes, kynſfolkes, and frendes graues praying not a few <hi>Deprofundis.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Fraunce.</head>
               <p>¶ In Fraunce I haue ſene and the cuſtome is that in euery maſſe ſayd by hyred prieſtes through all Fraunce ſuche a number of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profundis,</hi> as paſſeth my reckning that was euerye daye vſed in euerye Maſſe when the prieſte waſhed his handes after the Goſpell with holly water ſprinkled on the graue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>London.</head>
               <p>¶ I haue ſene my Lorde Mayre in London ryde to Powles Churche wyth greate tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphe accompanyed wyth his brethren the Aldermen and there ſayde or taryed and harde ſaye the <hi>Deprofundis</hi> vppon a Byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopes of London ſepulchre as ſayde was bounde yerely therevnto but now chaunged thankes be to god and to our learned biſhop chaunged I ſay into more godlines.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6058:8"/>
               <p>¶ I haue Preached my ſelfe at dyuers hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les of notable companyes which declared to me that they were bound to ſay all together <hi>De profundis</hi> for all Chriſtian ſoules after the ſeruice and banquette, and deſyred me to begine the <hi>De profundis,</hi> which I denyed, but yet I graunted to open, declare and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprete the trewe ſenſe of it to them if they wold gyue purifyed cares thervnto whiche thing they did, and after that did lyke the <hi>De profundis</hi> better then euer they dyd before as nowe manye in <hi>England</hi> do at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente tyme thankes be to God, which nowe do ſaye the Popes <hi>De profundis</hi> is deare of his <hi>De profundis</hi> but nowe thanckes be to god it is knowen to be a godlye prayer for the penitentes on lyfe and alſo for becauſe it dothe Intreate ſpeciallye of our Iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which is moſt neceſſarye to be knowen. &amp;c. Wherfore I thoughte it good to Intreate of this moſt godly Pſalme after my poore po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and learninge to kepe in the lighte of Iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the true Churche of God. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>¶ Note heare afore we beginne the texte that there is no ſaluation, grace nor iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, but onlye in God that wold not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute oure ſinnes, nor loke vppon them as Dauid ſayde. Thou haſt caſte all my ſinnes
<pb facs="tcp:6058:8"/>behinde thy backe o Lorde, thou haſte rente the decree of my Damnacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; alſo haſt frelye forgeuen all for Chriſtes ſake, therfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent ſupplicante muſte knowledge truſte and ſurely hope in the ſame, or elles he will euer be in doubte and diſpayre of hearinge hope and obtayninge by the temptations of Sata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he muſt knowledge him ſelf free from Hell, Death and from the yre of God. And ſo ſhall he pray with a ioyfull and quiete co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience &amp; ſure hope of Gods mercy throughe Ieſus Chriſt our Sauioure to whome with the Father, and the holye ghoſt bee all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glorye. Amen.</p>
               <p>¶ The Penitente Supplicante doth heare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wiſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſounding in his eares theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. <hi>Fili pecaſti ne aditias iterum ſed pro preſtinis peccatis precare Deum.</hi> That is to ſaye, My ſone thou haſte ſinned doe no more ſo, but praye vnto god for thy former ſinnes repentinge them depelye while thou haſte time defferinge not the ſame from day to daye, nor from yeare to yeare as manye do, which neuer do repent afore they ſe the panges of death vpon them,<note place="margin">Note well.</note> and ſo they do then repente for feare, and not for loue. Which is daungerous.</p>
               <p>¶ This Pſalme is a profunde prayer of a penitent ſinner, that is afrayed of the Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement
<pb facs="tcp:6058:9"/>of God agayuſte his ſinnes &amp; from the deepneſſe of hys harte and oute of the profunde Priſon of all ſinfullneſſe prayethe to God with a ſure Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence not onlye for him ſelfe, but for the aduerſities and tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of Chriſts hole Church and for al the poſteritie of Adam beinge in the Captiuitye of Satan and ſinne, knowledginge that he is euer prompte and more ready to geue, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are to aſke, which the Prophete ſayde in his perſon.<note place="margin">Eſay.</note> 
                  <hi>Antequam clamat exaudiam.</hi> That is or euer they crye I heare them and do helpe them as in example of the wydo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we, whiche broughte hyr Sone to bee bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed withoute the Portes of the Citye of Naham, where Chriſte dyde come vnloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for or called vppon and ſo reſtored him to lyfe agayne, with one worde. As he dyd Lazarus and many mo.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1-2" type="verse">
               <head>Deprofundis.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>¶ Oute of the Deepe haue I cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto the Lorde, Lord heare my voyce.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>¶ The Prayer of Dauid for hys ſynnes and for the deliueraunce of the Captiuitye of Babilone and for the aduerſities and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions of thoſe people, and all Godly peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb facs="tcp:6058:9"/>withoute ceaſinge hee prayed and cryed from the Deepeneſſe of his harte as he ſayd. <hi>Clamaui non tacui non deſperaui.</hi> That is to ſaye I cryed, I kepte not my peace I deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paried not, and as S. Paule ſayth to vs all Being in trouble. <hi>Sine intermiſsione orate aut bene agite.</hi> That is to ſay, Pray ye with out ceaſinge or elles do the thinge that good is, with perſeueraunce, takinge an example of the woman of Cananee which for hyr per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeueraunce and faythe was harde. So Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide cryed out of the Deepeneſſe of his hart and out of the deepe pryſons of ſinne, drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and myred in Deepe waters, that is to ſaye, into heauie afflictions as thoſe that ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denlye fall in the Deepe waters from the Deepeneſſe of theyr harte do crye for helpe, ſo this Pſalme and Godlye Prayer is ſette forthe by the Holy Ghoſt, for thoſe that bee afflicted and in tribulation and do acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge theyr Sinnes, and ſeeke for mercye from the bottome of theyr harts and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Deepe Pryſon of manyfolde and euill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſtences with great ſhame &amp; repentance of theyr ſinnes ſo ſayth S. Iero.<note place="margin">Ieromie.</note> 
                  <hi>Hoc quod homo agnoſcit Deus Ignoſcit.</hi> That is to ſay the ſinnes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> men do know God ſhal miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>know &amp; bleſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the Propher ſayth. <hi>Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus vir cui Dominus no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> imputat peccatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6058:10"/>man is ſaued but onlye by his mercy, &amp; not by merites deſeruinges, nor workes for as Sainte Paule ſayeth. <hi>Non ſunt condigni.</hi> They be neyther cleane, nor worthye of hys kingdome and glorie, for as S. Paule ſaith, the eyes cannot ſe, nor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hart can not thinke the thinges that god hathe prouided for his people, that do loue him, and if wee ſtomble or fall in anye kinde of ſinne, he hath apoin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted vs a reamedye, and that is to pray for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture ſayth. <hi>Cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ignoremus quid agere debeamus hoc ſolu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> habemus remedium vt oculos noſtros dirigamus ad te.</hi> That is to ſay: when we be troubled, or when wee know not what we ſhould do, he hath lefte vs this Kemedy to lifte vp oure eyes vnto him, and ſo Dauid ſaith, our forefathers did by theſe words. <hi>Cum tribularentur clama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerunt ad Dominum.</hi> When they were in trouble thy cryed vnto the Lord, and Dauid him ſelf ſayth. <hi>Cum tribularer ad Dominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> clamaui &amp; exaudiuit me.</hi> That is to ſaye, when I was in trouble I cryed to the lorde and he hard me, and ſo will he here all faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full penitents.</p>
               <p>¶ When this began to be taught in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, there was not a litell grudge of mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur amongeſt the people, ſaying: that they woulde do as their forefathers did, for then
<pb facs="tcp:6058:10"/>it was a good world as they ſayd why wold they not folow theyr forefathers in this to call vppon the Lord in their trouble as they did, but they did folowe blind teachers and guides of whome Chriſte dothe ſpeake, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaythe. <hi>Quando caecus caecum ducit am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo in foueam cadunt.</hi> That is to ſay, when the blinde leadethe the blinde, they do both fall in the pitte of dampnation, if they ſo perſeuere to follow the Pope, and his prou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de blind Shauelinges whiche was, and is the Authors &amp; mayntainers of this foreſayd blindeneſſe, and this is onlye the Rewarde, and frute that they ſhall haue of him. Let vs retourne to oure texte, which is. <hi>Apud Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum Miſericordia.</hi> To the faithfull and penitentes that doe beleue in the ſame and call for it, thy mercye and grace is aboue all thinges and thou arte the Fountayne oute of the whiche it ſpringethe continually and Frelye thou offereſt vs the ſame, but not to hym that is contumaxe and proterue and make them ſelfes vnworthye of the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="verse">
               <head>Et copioſa apud eum <hi>Redemptio.</hi>
               </head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>And before hym a plenteouſe Redemption.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <pb facs="tcp:6058:11"/>
               <p>¶ But alas the greateſt number of men do ſhute their eyes at this, &amp; at theyr owne vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces &amp; ſo they ſlepe in theyr ſinnes and extrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me Ignoraunce in ſo muche that no man dothe acknoweledge God to bee mercyfull and ſo they take no paynes to Inuocate or call for mercy, but the godly ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate with him ſelf y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god is mercyfull and geueth vs frely for it is only in hys hands &amp; power to geue it &amp; in none other. And mercy is euer before his eyes. <hi>Miſericordia &amp; non Ira.</hi> That is to ſaye, Mercye &amp; not Yre and the plenteouſe redemption, of hys ſone and oure Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt. <hi>Non parua ſed copioſa redemptio.</hi> That is not a litell re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, but a copiouſe &amp; plenteouſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption &amp; beſides him there is no Rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Paule declareth brieſly ſaying. <hi>Iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur Gratis gratia ipſius per redemptione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> qui eſt in Chriſto Ieſu.</hi> that is to ſay, we are Iuſtified and made righteous by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption that is in Chriſte Ieſu freelye. <hi>pro nihilo ſaluos facies eos, &amp; hoc non ex nobis.</hi> And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> not by oure ſelfes. <hi>Sed Dei donum eſt.</hi> But it is a gefte of God. <hi>Et non ex operibus ne quis glorietur.</hi> And not of works y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhold glorye of him ſelfe &amp; ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſcripture ſayth. <hi>No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ex operibꝰ Iuſtitiae quo nos fecimus ſed ſecundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> miſericordia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <pb facs="tcp:6058:11"/>ſaluos nos fecit,</hi> that is to ſaye not of the workes that we doe but throughe his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye hee hathe ſaued vs for if it were of woorkes then it were not by grace, <hi>Per memetipſum iuraui dicit Dominus nolo mortem Peccatoris ſed magis vt Peniteat &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uertatur &amp; viuat.</hi> that is to ſaye I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ſworne by my ſelfe ſaythe the Lorde I will not the deathe of a ſinner but rather thae hee ſhoulde repente and conuerte and bee ſaued,<note place="margin">Nota.</note> 
                  <hi>O beatos &amp; felices homines in quorum cauſa Deus iurat,</hi> O bleſſed and happye are thoſe men in whoſe cauſe God dothe ſweare. <hi>Et O miſeros qui Deo iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rante non credunt,</hi> that is to ſaye that miſerable and wretched are thoſe which doe not beleeue god when he dothe ſweare that cannot ſaye the thinge that is not trewe but veritie it ſelfe, heare he will that all the hope of the godlye ſorte ſhoulde be in his mercye oute of the whiche hope ſpryngethe a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious Redemption becauſe in the handes of God there is an infynite number to vs and Incredible wayes that God hathe to ſaue vs for hys mercye is aboue all hys workes and he dothe neuer forget to poure oute mercye <hi>Ergo</hi> he nedes no interceſſors nor medyatours al be it agaynſte the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture they make many. But the holy ghoſt
<pb facs="tcp:6058:12"/>ſaithe <hi>Vnus eſt mediator noſter Ergo non ſunt plures,</hi> therfore there be not many ergo they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> doe make many, doe ſinne againſt the holy goſt. The ſeeing &amp; the feeling of Gods iudgement in our hartes &amp; conſciences doth engender hatred, &amp; fleyng from god without the hope of his mercy &amp; that is very apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſye &amp; rebellion &amp; ſo we ſhall neuer be perta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of this plenteous redemption for one droppe of that immaculate bloud hathe bene ſufficient to redeme the hole worlde &amp; yet he cryeth vpon vs by his holy word and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes ſaying as teſtifieth S. Iohn <hi>Sanguis Ieſu Chriſti Immundat nos ab omni pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cato,</hi> that is to ſay the bloud of Ieſu Chriſte doth waſhe vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all our ſinnes and as the ſcripture ſaith, <hi>Mundi eſtis Iuſtificati eſtis, ſanguine eius,</hi> that is to ſaye, you are made cleane &amp; waſhed, <hi>Venite &amp; haurite de fon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus ſaluatoris.</hi> by his bloud &amp; not by gold ſiluer nor precious ſtones, for the kingdome of god is not bought for money. Which run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth copiouſty at handes, feete, and hart, and neuer is drye, therfore it maye be well called a copious redemption as hee commaundeth them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery godly ſhould come and taſt of thoſe fountaines &amp; not ſo contemptuouſlye as do the vngodly &amp; caſt awayes, the which ſweare ſo oft by the lordes bloude, <hi>Venite &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:6058:12"/>haurite de fontibus ſaluatoris,</hi> that is to ſay to the vnlearned come &amp; taſt of the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of your redemer &amp; ſauiour receyuing the vertue of the ſame for if he redeeme not Iſraell from all their iniquities &amp; ſinnes he ſhoulde ceaſe from his office therefore let vs geue vigilant labours that our ſinnes maye be put away &amp; that we may retourne to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine his grace &amp; fauoure. &amp;c. As Dauid dyd which diſpayred not nor withdrew himſelfe from god for the multitude of his ſinnes but for the anger of God he ſought for his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and from God that wonded to God that healed the woundes of his harte which ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man nor Angell coulde heale.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="verse">
               <head>Et propter legem tuam ſuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nui <hi>te Domine.</hi>
               </head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>For thy lawe, ſake I haue taryed &amp; loked for thy mercy, and truſted in the ſame how gilty that euer my ſoule is.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>¶ For in all thy lawe newe and olde, thou haſt promiſed mercy to true penitentes and beleuers in the Lorde, for thy promiſes ſake graunt me the ſame for I embrace thy wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and promiſes &amp; do beleue the ſame, and in ſo doing I promiſe my ſelfe ſaluation, for becauſe thy promyſes cannot lye, nor thy</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6058:13"/>
               <p>¶ <hi>Quamdiu Viuet Iſraell ſperet in Chriſto.</hi> That is as long as a true chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do liue let him truſt in the lord both in proſperitie and in aduerſitie by night &amp; day. O how happye is he that oftentimes remembreth his ſinnes with hope of mercye, and ſeekes the ſame at the handes of the Lorde, &amp; heare let vs ſaye with S. Peter. <hi>Verbum Vite habes,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay thou haſt the worde of life, and the keyes of Dauid for thou doſt ſhut and no man can open, &amp; thou doſt open and no man can ſhut. Heare I might ſpeake of watches kept both in the olde &amp; new lawe but for prolixneſſe I will not be tedious but I will remember to put my truſt in the lord &amp; to no other, keping his preceptes and rules with thanks geuing to his maieſtie for the ſame, and not ſayinge with the Fryers &amp; the monckes, that doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde more the preceptes &amp; the keping of S. Fraunces and S. Dominickes &amp; doe geue greter thankes for that as I haue hard with mine eares.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="verse">
               <head>Et ipſe redimet Iſrael ex <hi>om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus Iniquitatibus eius.</hi>
               </head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>And he ſhall redeme Iſraell from all his ſynnes.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>¶ De ſaythe not onelye of one ſinne or one
<pb facs="tcp:6058:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>iniquitie but of all but contrarye to him dyd the Pope that would giue pardons for ſome and reſerued other ſome to the comming to himſelf, <hi>Sed ip ſe redimet Iſrael &amp;, non alius</hi> for he himſelfe hath redemed Iſraell and no body ells but he, and that is to vnderſtande all Chriſtian &amp; faithfull people as the angell teſtifyethe to Zacharie ſayinge, <hi>Ipſe ſaluum faciet Populum ſuum a peccatis eoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> that is to ſaye he ſhall ſaue all hys people from their ſinnes his people is the faithefull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation and no other,<note place="margin">mat 10.</note> nor yet ſhalbe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of this redemption, whiche is to the godly a great comforte and conſolation that he hathe redeemed Iſraell from all their ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities what ſoeuer, and what kinde of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities ſo euer they were or ſinnes and that freelye. It is greate foliſhenes to thinke that god wil not forgeue ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes vntill the time that he be pleaſed wyth our good workes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="colophon">
               <p>
                  <hi>¶ JMPRINTED at London by Thomas Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foote</hi> for William Norton. (<g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>)</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
